Guide to the Calvin Bryce Hoover Papers, 1922-1970
Duke University. University Archives
Calvin Bryce Hoover papers 1922-1970
Hoover, Calvin B. (Calvin Bryce), 1897-
41.5 linear feet Extent: 40,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Calvin Bryce Hoover (1897-1974) was an economist, a scholar, and a leader in public service. A member of the Duke faculty from 1925 until his retirement in 1966, Hoover served as chairman of the Department of Economics from 1937-1957, and Dean of the Graduate School from 1938-1948. Hoover is widely accepted as the founder of the field of comparative economics. Materials include correspondence, departmental files, reports, photographs, sound recordings, books, articles, clippings, scrapbooks, date books, and other printed materials. Major subjects of the collection are the economic conditions in the Soviet Union, Germany, and the United States in the 20th century; the administration of an academic department during wartime; Soviet economic policy; Soviet politics and government; the formation of New Deal agricultural policies in the South; and the Office of Strategic Services. English, German, and Russian.
UA.29.02.0044
Language: English, German, and Russian.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Calvin Bryce Hoover Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973 (A73-2), 1974 (A74-4), 1986, and 1988 (A88-8).
Biographical Note
Calvin Bryce Hoover (1897-1974) was an economist, a scholar, and a leader in public service. A member of the Duke faculty from 1925 until his retirement in 1966, Hoover served as chairman of the Department of Economics from 1937-1957, and Dean of the Graduate School from 1938-1948.
Hoover was born in Berwick, Illinois on April 14, 1897. He attended Monmouth College, but his student days were interrupted by World War I. Hoover belonged to the 123rd Field Artillery Regiment, U.S. Army, American Expeditionary Forces, and fought at the battles of St. Mihiel and Meuse Argonne. As a corporal, Hoover left the Army and graduated from Monmouth College in 1922. After a brief stint of farming, Hoover decided on an academic career and received his Ph.D. from the University of Wisconsin in 1926. He also received Litt.D. degrees from Columbia University and Monmouth College, and a Doctor of Laws degree from Case Western Reserve University.
Hoover came to Duke in 1925 and remained until his retirement in 1966. He was assistant professor (1925-1927), professor of economics (1927-1950), James B. Duke Professor of Economics (1950-1967), and chairman of the Department of Economics and Business Administration (1937-1957).
From 1920 through 1958, Hoover studied, taught and undertook research in the Soviet Union, Germany, Italy, France, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Sweden, and Norway. His long history of government service began in 1933 when he became economic advisor to the Department of Agriculture. During World War II, Hoover was an Office of Strategic Services official for Northern Europe and Poland, and oversaw the invasion of Germany from those areas for the O.S.S.
After the war, as chairman of the German Standard of Living Board and advisor to General Lucius Clay, Hoover prepared the Hoover Report, which established Germany's postwar level of production. He was an active participant in the implementation of the Marshall Plan, and the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development. In 1947, Hoover was awarded the Medal of Freedom.
Professionally, Hoover was a member of the Southern Economic Association, the American Economic Association, the Association for Comparative Economics. He was a fellow of the Royal Economic Society. Hoover served as President of the S.E.A. in 1937 and of the A.E.A. in 1953, the first Southerner so honored. In 1965, Hoover was awarded the A.E.A. Distinguished Fellow Award. His publications were prodigious, with eight books to his credit and one hundred articles.
His books include: Economic Life of Soviet Russia; Germany Enters The Third Reich; Dictators and Democracies; International Trade and Domestic Employment; Economic Resources and Policies of the South; and The Economy, Liberty, and the State. His autobiography, Memoirs of Capitalism, Communism and Nazism, was published in 1965. He contributed numerous articles to newspapers, magazines and professional journals.
Hoover served as President of the American Economic Association (the first Southerner to attain that distinction), the Comparative Economics Association, and the Southern Economic Association; and was elected a Fellow of the Royal Economic Society. Hoover is widely accepted as the founder of the field of comparative economics. Socially, Hoover was a member of several prestigious clubs, including the Century Club of New York, the Cosmos Club and Gridiron Club, both of Washington, D.C., the Watauga Club of North Carolina, and the Newcomen Society and Question Club of Duke University.
Hoover married Faith Miriam Sprole in 1919. They had two daughters, Carol Faith and Sylvia Joan. Hoover retired from Duke University in 1966 and died in 1974.
Parts of the Biographical Note were adapted from Calvin Bryce Hoover, http://www.econ.duke.edu/History/Hoover/hoover.html
Collection Overview
The Calvin Bryce Hoover papers span the years 1922-1970, with the bulk falling between 1929 and 1968. The collection is arranged into nine series: Correspondence; Writings; Academic Materials; Professional Associations; Government Service; Subject Files; Audio-Visual Material; Personal; and Printed Material. The collection includes correspondence, departmental files, reports, photographs, sound recordings, books, articles, clippings, scrapbooks, date books, and other printed materials.
The first series, Correspondence, contains mostly academic or professional correspondence. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically, except for Box 27 which contains correspondence from or about the National Planning Association. It is important to note that Hoover tended to file his correspondence by subject, rather than by correspondent. As such, a file labeled "John Doe" may not necessarily contain correspondence written by "John Doe," but may include correspondence about "John Doe."
The second series, Writings, includes copies of Hoover's publications, unpublished material, addresses, drafts, notes, publication agreements, and correspondence. The third series, Academic Material, includes departmental files, course files, and other materials associated largely with Hoover's work at Duke University. The series includes material about the Economics Dept., professors, courses taught by Hoover, correspondence, theses, and other files. The fourth series, Professional Associations, includes files on the American Economic Association, the Southern Economic Association, and the Ford Foundation.
The fifth series, Government Service, includes general subject files, files on war agencies, the Committee for Economic Development, and the Council on Foreign Relations, the Economic Cooperation Administration, and correspondence. The sixth series, Subject Files, includes general topical files. The seventh series, Audio-Visual Material, includes photographs and audio reels. The eighth series, Personal, includes Hoover's personal school papers, souvenirs, and personal papers belonging to Hoover's wife, Faith.
The ninth series, Printed Material, includes publications not authored by Hoover. There are a fair number of these in German and Russian.
This collection contains materials that would lend itself to many areas of research interests. Of note is the material pertaining to the Office of Strategic Services (O.S.S.) which offers a unique picture of the work of the O.S.S. in Scandinavia, the Chief of Mission in Stockholm, Hoover's administrative style and means of controlling this operation, his philosophy of intelligence, and many day to day details of the profession of espionage.
Other topics of interest include the administration of an academic department during wartime, Soviet economic data and collection techniques of the 1930s, the formation of New Deal agricultural policies, and the development of the American foreign aid program.
Subject Headings
Communism -- Soviet Union; Comparative economics; Duke University. Dept. of Economics; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Graduate School; Economics; Economics -- History; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Economists -- Correspondence; Economists -- United States; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Germany -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; Hoover, Calvin B. (Calvin Bryce), 1897-; Reconstruction (1939-1951) -- Europe; Southern States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-; Soviet Union -- Economic policy; Soviet Union -- Economic conditions; Soviet Union -- Politics and government; United States -- Economic policy; United States. Office of Strategic Services; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects; Clippings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings
Contents of Collection
- General Correspondence
  - A (miscellaneous), 1928-1952 (Box 1)
  - A (miscellaneous), 1953-1966 (Box 1)
  - Abert, James G. (Box 1)
  - Acheson, Dean, 1946-1966 (Box 1)
  - Agriculture, Dept. of, 1947-1957 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Clark Lee, 1944-1959 (Box 1)
  - Alt, Richard M., 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Alumni (Dept. of Alumni Affairs), 1966 (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Sciences, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - American Assembly, Registration, 1964 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1966 (Box 1)
  - American Farm and Economic Association, 1939-1954 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Labor, 1958 (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - American Telephone and Telegraph Co., 1966 (Box 1)
  - Amiotte, Madame Victor, 1937-1957 (Box 1)
  - Appalachian State Teachers College Institute, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Arizona Trip (Dr. Richard Harvill), 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - Arkansas State College, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish, 1944-1958 (Box 2)
  - Arts Council (Box 2)
  - Ashbrook, Arthur G., Jr., 1947-1961 (Box 2)
  - Ashburn, Karl E., 1930-1967 (Box 2)
  - Association for Comparative Economics, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Australian Wool, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Author, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - A.V.C. Corporation, 1967 (Box 2)
  - B (miscellaneous), 1928-1955 (Box 2)
  - B (miscellaneous), 1956-1969 (Box 3)
  - Bauer, Peter T., 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Bell, J.W., 1953-1959 (Box 3)
  - Beloit, Wisconsin, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Bergson, Abram, 1956-1963 (Box 3)
  - Berry, Thomas S., 1946-1958 (Box 3)
  - Biography, World, 1947-1952 (Box 3)
  - Blaisdell, Thomas C., Jr., 1936-1940 (Box 3)
  - Blomgren, Oscar C., 1952-1960 (Box 3)
  - Blough, Roy, 1949-1953 (Box 3)
  - Bonn, Prof. M.J., 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - Bonnen, James T., 1950-1968 (Box 3)
  - Book Reviews, 1939-1944 (Box 3)
  - Bowden, Elbert V., 1952-1967 (Box 3)
  - Bowie, Robert R., 1946-1967 (Box 3)
  - Boyd, James, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
  - Brandis, Royall, 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Branscombe, Harvie, 1946-1951 (Box 3)
  - Bressman, Earl N., 1935-1949 (Box 3)
  - Breswick, William N., 1947-1959 (Box 3)
  - Brice, Ashbel G., 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Briley, John Marshall, 1946-1962 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institute, 1947-1965 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institute Seminar, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
  - Browne-Mayers, Charlotte, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Bryan, Malcolm H., 1946-1950 (Box 4)
  - Bundy, McGeorge, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Bunn, Ronald F., 1956-1958 (Box 4)
  - Bureau of the Census Executive Reserve, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Business, School of (Duke), 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - Butter, Irene Hasenberg, 1959-1962 (Box 4)
  - C (miscellaneous), 1924-1952 (Box 4)
  - C (miscellaneous), 1953-1957 (Box 4)
  - C (miscellaneous), 1958-1957 (Box 4)
  - California Trip, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Canada, Seminar, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Canadian Institute, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Capital Research and Management Co., 1954 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1944-1950 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Corporation of NY, 1948-1953 (Box 4)
  - Case Western Reserve (Honorary Doctorate), 1968 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Research Grants, 1947-1949 (Box 5)
  - Carter, "Nick" Travel Club, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Cartter, Alan, 1962-1964 (Box 5)
  - Cassels, John M., 1950-1966 (Box 5)
  - Castle, C.A., 1952-1957 (Box 5)
  - Century Club, 1949-1965 (Box 5)
  - Chace, Hugh R., 1955, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Challenge (magazine), 1959-1962 (Box 5)
  - Challenge (magazine), 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Chamberlain, Neil W., 1954-1965 (Box 5)
  - Charlesworth, James C., 1959 (Box 5)
  - Chicago University Lectures, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Chicago Roundtable, 1943-1952 (Box 5)
  - Chicago University Seminar, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Christensen, C.L., 1956 (Box 5)
  - Christgau, Victor, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Civil Service, 1935-1959 (Box 5)
  - Claremont Men's College (California), 1954-1955 (Box 6)
  - Clark, J.M., 1935-1962 (Box 6)
  - Clay, Lucious D., 1945-1949 (Box 6)
  - Clyde, Paul, 1946-1967 (Box 6)
  - Cocke, Norman A., 1960-1962 (Box 6)
  - Codex, Princeton Meetings, 1953-1967 (Box 6)
  - Cohn, Stanley H., 1965 (Box 6)
  - Cole, R. Taylor, 1948-1968 (Box 6)
  - Collyer, John L. (BF Goodrich), 1947-1964 (Box 6)
  - Colmer Committee, 1944-1947 (Box 6)
  - Colt, Henry F., 1947-1948 (Box 6)
  - Columbia University, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
  - Columbia University Press, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Commencement Speech, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Commencement, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Commerce, Dept. of (Kaldor, David), 1949-1950 (Box 6)
  - Commerce, Dept. of (International trade), 1950 (Box 6)
  - Committee for Economic Development, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
  - Committee for Economic Development, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Committee for Economic Development, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Russian and East European Studies, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Commons, Jack, 1930-1949 (Box 7)
  - Commonwealth Studies, 1955-1966 (Box 7)
  - Comparative Economic Association, 1963-1965 (Box 7)
  - Connery, Robert H., 1951-1958 (Box 7)
  - Conservatives in Power, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
  - Copeland, William LeRoy, 1948-1949 (Box 7)
  - COSMOS Club, 1949-1967 (Box 8)
  - COSMOS Travel Bureau, 1960-1963 (Box 8)
  - Council of Economic Advisors, 1948-1954 (Box 8)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1945-1958 (Box 8)
  - Cowles, John, 1962-1964 (Box 8)
  - Crittenden, Christopher, 1944-1957 (Box 8)
  - Crowther, Geoffrey, 1949-1955 (Box 8)
  - CURRENT (Digest of the Soviet Press, 1955-1962 (Box 8)
  - D (miscellaneous), 1930-1949 (Box 8)
  - D (miscellaneous), 1952-1966 (Box 8)
  - Daniels, Jonathan, 1946-1952 (Box 8)
  - Davies, David G., 1963-1966 (Box 8)
  - Davis, Chester C., 1936-1960 (Box 8)
  - Davis, J.S., 1960 (Box 8)
  - Davison, Dean W.C., 1947-1952 (Box 8)
  - DeAlessi, Louis, 1963-1965 (Box 9)
  - Deener, David R., 1966 (Box 9)
  - Delaplane, Walter H., 1956-1963 (Box 9)
  - de Vyver, Frank T., 1960-1965 (Box 9)
  - Dewey, Donald, 1956-1960 (Box 9)
  - Dewhurst, J. Frederic, 1951-1956 (Box 9)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1962-1965 (Box 9)
  - Donovan, Major General William, J., 1941-1958 (Box 9)
  - Douglas, Paul H., 1955-1965 (Box 9)
  - Douwaji, Ghazi, 1963-1966 (Box 9)
  - Draper, General William, Jr., 1945-1967 (Box 9)
  - Duke-related, 1933-1934 (Box 9)
  - Dukes, Charles A., 1949-1963 (Box 9)
  - Durham, Carl T., 1945-1949 (Box 9)
  - E (miscellaneous), 1931-1966 (Box 9)
  - Earle, Edward Mead, 1941-1952 (Box 9)
  - Eastern Airlines, 1949-1964 (Box 9)
  - Eastman, Harry Claude, 1949-1952 (Box 9)
  - Economic and Business Foundation, 1944-1945 (Box 9)
  - Economic History Association, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Economic Systems of the West (requests for), 1958 (Box 9)
  - Edens, A. Hollis, 1949-1957 (Box 9)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - Eiteman, W. J., 1942-1950 (Box 10)
  - El Kammash, Magdi, 1961-1966 (Box 10)
  - Elliott, George A., 1957 (Box 10)
  - Elliott, W. Y., 1945-1954 (Box 10)
  - Emory University, 1950 (Box 10)
  - Enke, Stephen, 1961-1963 (Box 10)
  - Ervin, Sam J., 1956-1967 (Box 10)
  - Everett, Pauline, 1948-1951 (Box 10)
  - F (miscellaneous), 1930-1968 (Box 10)
  - Family-related, 1933-1968 (Box 10)
  - Fanning, J. W., 1967 (Box 10)
  - Farioletti, Marius, 1953 (Box 10)
  - Ferguson, Charles E., 1964-1966 (Box 10)
  - Few, W. P., 1934-1936, 1953 (Mrs. W. P. Few) (Box 10)
  - Fike, Edward, 1948-1951 (Box 10)
  - Fisher, Irving, 1944-1946 (Box 10)
  - Flowers, R. L., 1930-1949 (Box 10)
  - Ford, Capital Study, Southern Economic Journal, 1960-1965 (Box 10)
  - Foreign Affairs, 1944-1962 (Box 10)
  - Foreign Policy Association, 1939-1946 (Box 11)
  - Foster, Maxwell, 1951-1961 (Box 11)
  - Free Europe University in Exile, 1954 (Box 11)
  - G (miscellaneous), 1930-1968 (Box 11)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1952-1965 (Box 11)
  - Garner, Paul, 1961, 1964 (Box 11)
  - General Education Board, 1944-1954 (Box 11)
  - Gottheil, Fred M., 1959-1967 (Box 11)
  - Goodwin, Craufurd, 1958-1965 (Box 11)
  - Graduate Students (A-M), circa 1956-1966 (Box 11)
  - Graduate Students (N-Z), circa 1960s (Box 12)
  - Graham, Frank P., 1946-1949 (Box 12)
  - Gramley, Lyle E., 1954-1955 (Box 12)
  - Gray, Gordon, 1946-1960 (Box 12)
  - Griffith, William J., 1961 (Box 12)
  - Gross, Paul M., 1947-1966 (Box 12)
  - Gulledge, S. L., Jr., 1962 (Box 12)
  - H (miscellaneous), 1929-1949 (Box 12)
  - H (miscellaneous), 1950-1967 (Box 12)
  - Hanes, P. Guber, 1960, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Harriman, Averell, 1947-1950 (Box 12)
  - Harris, Seymour E., 1948-1962 (Box 12)
  - Hart, Deryl, 1960-1966 (Box 12)
  - Hartle, Douglas, 1958-1959 (Box 12)
  - Harvard Ad Hoc Committee Meeting, 1956-1957 (Box 12)
  - Harvard Business Review, 1959 (Box 13)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers, 1959-1965 (Box 13)
  - Harvill, Richard A., 1959-1969 (Box 13)
  - Hays, Brooks, 1947, 1960, 1962 (Box 13)
  - Hegeland, Hugo, 1956-1967 (Box 13)
  - High School Text (Joint Council on Economic Education), circa 1964-1966 (Box 13)
  - Hildebrand, George, 1958-1959 (Box 13)
  - Hobbs, Marcus E., 1957, 1959 (Box 13)
  - Hoeffding, Waldemar, 1948-1950, 1961 (Box 13)
  - Hoffman, Paul G., 1948-1959 (Box 13)
  - Holmes, John W., 1957, 1963 (Box 13)
  - Hood, William C., 1957 (Box 13)
  - Hoover Dinner, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Hoover, Faith (Road Lobbying Efforts), 1949 (Box 13)
  - Letters (originals) written to his wife, Faith, while Hoover was in Russia, 1929 Aug.-1930 May (Box 14)
  - Letters (copies) written to his wife, Faith, while Hoover was in Russia, 1929 Aug.-1930 May (Box 14)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1947-1948 (Box 14)
  - Hoover, Leonora, 1932, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Hoover, Sylvia, 1949 (Box 14)
  - Horwood, Owen, 1962-1964 (Box 14)
  - "Hot" Jobs, 1958-1962 (Box 14)
  - Hotel de Crillon (Paris), 1950-1958 (Box 14)
  - Humble Oil and Refining Company, 1966-1967 (Box 14)
  - Huntington, W. Chapin, 1945-1946 (Box 14)
  - I (miscellaneous), 1941-1965 (Box 14)
  - Illinois, University of, 1956 (Box 14)
  - Institute of Post-War Reconstruction, 1943-1944 (Box 14)
  - Insurance (Aetna), 1939, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Insurance for Teachers, 1952-1956 (Box 15)
  - Intercultural Publications, 1954 (Box 15)
  - International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1963-1966 (Box 15)
  - J (miscellaneous), 1929-1968 (Box 15)
  - James B. Duke Professorship Committee, 1961-1963 (Box 15)
  - Japan, 1957 (Box 15)
  - Jobs Available, 1966 (Box 15)
  - Johnson C. Smith University, 1966-1967 (Box 15)
  - Joint Economic Committee, 1955-1967 (Box 15)
  - Jordan, B. Everett, 1959-1967 (Box 15)
  - Jordan, Charles E., 1950-1966 (Box 15)
  - K (miscellaneous), 1930-1966 (Box 15)
  - Karmel, Peter H., 1955-1956 (Box 15)
  - Kassalow, Everett M., 1959 (Box 15)
  - Kellogg, Lester S., 1954 (Box 15)
  - Kennan, George F., 1947-1965 (Box 15)
  - Kennedy, John W., 1959-1963 (Box 15)
  - Keynes, John Maynard, 1930-1959 (Box 15)
  - Keys, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Kittila, R. S., 1959-1967 (Box 15)
  - Knauerhase, Ramon, 1968 (Box 15)
  - Knickerbocker, H. R., 1947 (Box 15)
  - Knight, Douglas M., 1963-1965 (Box 15)
  - Knox College, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Kobayashi, Kunihiko, 1956-1963 (Box 16)
  - Koefod, Paul E., 1960-1968 (Box 16)
  - Kornegay, Horace R., 1961-1966 (Box 16)
  - Kreps, Clifton H., Jr., 1955 (Box 16)
  - Kreps, Juanita, 1947, 1955, 1960 (Box 16)
  - Kyklos, 1947-1956 (Box 16)
  - L (miscellaneous), 1930-1967 (Box 16)
  - Lagos, Ricardo, 1963-1964 (Box 16)
  - Langer, William L., 1965 (Box 16)
  - Lanning, John Tate, 1959-1965 (Box 16)
  - Lawson, Arthur, 1960-1963 (Box 16)
  - Leighton, Richard, 1959-1967 (Box 16)
  - Leutze, J. R., 1967 (Box 16)
  - Linder, Harold, 1958-1963 (Box 16)
  - Lloyd, Peter J., 1962-1964 (Box 16)
  - Loucks, W. N., 1956-1959 (Box 16)
  - Lovell, C. A. Knox, 1964-1966 (Box 16)
  - M (miscellaneous), 1930-1967 (Box 17)
  - Mc (miscellaneous), 1930-1932, 1941, 1960, 1963-1966 (Box 17)
  - McCormick, Edward T., 1948-1963 (Box 17)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1947-1962 (Box 17)
  - McLean, Donald H., Jr., 1947 (Box 17)
  - MacMillan Co., 1930-1938 (Box 17)
  - MacMurray, J.V.A., 1931-1932 (Box 17)
  - Machlup, Fritz, 1960-1961 (Box 17)
  - Mansfield, Edwin, 1954-1963 (Box 17)
  - Mansfield, Mike, 1956-1967 (Box 17)
  - Markham, Jesse, 1957 (Box 17)
  - Medicare, 1966 (Box 17)
  - Means, Gardiner, 1961 (Box 17)
  - Miller, Francis P., 1939-1961 (Box 18)
  - Miller, Helen Hill, 1941-1952 (Box 18)
  - Milton, George Fort, 1944-1948 (Box 18)
  - Minnesota, University of, 1938-1939 (Box 18)
  - Monmouth College, 1952-1966 (Box 18)
  - Moroney, John R., 1967-1969 (Box 18)
  - Mosely, Philip E., 1954-1969 (Box 18)
  - Mulligan, Paul F., 1965-1967 (Box 18)
  - Myrdal, Gunnar, 1947-1950 (Box 18)
  - N (miscellaneous), circa 1928-1966 (Box 18)
  - Nathan, Otto, 1938-1966 (Box 18)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc., 1961-1965 (Box 18)
  - National Security Council, 1959-1960 (Box 18)
  - National Science Foundation, 1960-1962 (Box 18)
  - National War College, 1949-1966 (Box 18)
  - National War College, 1946-1948 (Box 19)
  - Nazi Economic System (book project), 1966-1967 (Box 19)
  - New Leader, The, 1957-1963 (Box 19)
  - Newman, Richard R., 1945-1967 (Box 19)
  - New York Times, 1935-1961 (Box 19)
  - Nichols, T. Everett, Jr., 1962-1964 (Box 19)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1950-1967 (Box 19)
  - North Carolina Educational Council of National Purposes, 1964 (Box 19)
  - Nutter, Warren, 1956-1957 (Box 19)
  - O (miscellaneous), 1931-1967 (Box 19)
  - Office of Education Wartime Commission, 1941-1942 (Box 19)
  - O'Leary, James J., 1949-1967 (Box 19)
  - Oliver, Henry M., 1955-1965 (Box 19)
  - P (miscellaneous), 1930-1967 (Box 19)
  - Personal, 1930-1933, 1956, 1959 (Box 19)
  - Personal, 1942 (Box 19)
  - Personal, 1943 (Box 20)
  - Peske, Edgar, 1960-1963 (Box 20)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1950-1959 (Box 20)
  - Photographs and Portraits, 1966 (Box 20)
  - Powell, B.E. [Benjamin], 1962-1966 (Box 20)
  - Prentice Hall, Inc., 1963 (Box 20)
  - Professional, 1929-1934 (Box 20)
  - Public Affairs Institute, 1946-1950 (Box 20)
  - Publications Committee, 1962 (Box 20)
  - Puccinelli, Mrs. Albert, 1951-1952 (Box 20)
  - Pugh, Olin S., 1952-1956 (Box 20)
  - Pusey, Nathan N., 1956 (Box 20)
  - Q (miscellaneous), 1959, 1965 (Box 20)
  - R (miscellaneous), 1930-1967 (Box 20)
  - Ratchford, C.B., 1949-1964 (Box 20)
  - Ratchford, B.U., 1960-1968 (Box 20)